A paradox is an idea, image, or story that (at
first glance, at least) seems to contain some
contradiction, or at least to go against
logic and our deepest intuitions.
Do you like this whole paradox thing?  Well, do
n't miss this video because I'm going to tell you
10 key paradoxes from the History of Philosophy
that you absolutely have to know if you want a
more philosophical life.  Also, I think
that practically none of you will
know the last two, because at least I have not seen them
explained on YouTube in Spanish.  Let's go!
(1)
The paradox of the ship of Theseus.
Collected by the historian
Plutarch, who trained at the
Platonic Academy during the 1st century AD, it asks us to
imagine the ship in which Theseus returned
from Crete after having killed the mythical
Minotaur.  Apparently, a legend tells
that the Athenians preserved this boat for
centuries and centuries, replacing the old planks
as they wore out with
newer ones.  And now the question is: if we replace
all the parts of the ship, do we still have
the same ship?  And let's add a twist:
if we build another identical ship with the old pieces
, which of the two is
Theseus' ship?  The old one, the new one, or both?  Tell me what
you think in the comments!  This paradox has
delighted philosophers throughout
the ages and has been used to reflect
on what constitutes the identity of a
thing that changes over time.
We can even transfer it to ourselves,
which produces
much more "DISTURDY" results.
Today, for example, we know that every so
often most of the cells in our
body are replaced by new cells.
So, am I the same person I was when I was born?
L: Great, great!  Thank you so much
for giving me an existential crisis:
the mother who gave birth to you.  E: Well, wait, do
you want me to blow your mind even more?
L: No, no, no, thank you, thank you.  E: Well,
this paradox makes me think that
when someone is teleported in a movie like Star
Trek, they
are actually destroying them and building
a copy of the original person somewhere else.
L: You.  Hate.
(2) The arrow paradox.
Posed by the philosopher
Zeno of Elea, the paradox
of the arrow was one of the many aporias of
movement that he used to reinforce the thesis
of his teacher Parmenides, who had said that
change was impossible and contrary to reason.
Imagine an archer shooting an arrow at
a target.  The arrow is ejected in a
more or less parabolic motion until it finally reaches
its target.  You're not going to complain, it's easy to
imagine.  But there's a problem here, says Zeno.
Because if we divide this movement into instants,
at each instant the arrow is at rest, occupying
a specific place.  If we think of an instant,
the arrow cannot be in motion,
because for it to be in motion there would have to
be a period of time, which
by definition does not occur in an instant:
ergo it has to be at rest at every
instant.  But the sum of many rests,
even of infinite rests, cannot give
rise to movement, that is absurd,
contradictory!  Therefore, although our senses
tell us that there is movement, that the arrow moves,
our reason shows us that this is impossible.
(3) The paradox of Achilles and the tortoise.
Another of
Zeno's favorite paradoxes to reinforce the
same point was that of Achilles and the
tortoise.  Achilles, the great Greek hero,
decides to challenge a tortoise to a race.
L: And why is that?
E: Zenón doesn't explain it to him,
but what do I know, maybe he was bored.
L: Well, I get bored and I don't do those things.
Since Achilles wants to play fair, he
gives the tortoise a
10-meter head start.  Little did he know that this
advantage would make the race a
much more difficult task to complete than
the 12 labors of Hercules.  Because when
Achilles reaches 10 meters, the tortoise
will have gained a small advantage:
let's say one meter.  And when
Achilles reaches that meter,
the turtle will have advanced 10 centimeters.
And when Achilles recovers that distance,
the tortoise will have already advanced one centimeter.
Etcetera, etcetera, etcetera, etcetera.
The conclusion, absurd for all intents and purposes, is
that Achilles will never be able to overtake the tortoise,
because the latter will always maintain a certain advantage,
however small it may be.  Again, reason contradicts
what the senses show us, which in
Zeno's eyes (pun intended) demonstrates the
irrational and illusory nature of movement.
Basically, Zeno's paradoxes consist in
pointing out that any movement or translation
between two points implies having completed,
having crossed an infinite number of points or
distances.  Since infinity cannot be traversed,
movement (which implies traversing an
infinity) must be impossible,
however contrary this may be to the
testimony of the senses.
(4) Achilles and the tortoise (logical version).
In the s.  In the 19th century, Lewis Carroll (mathematician and author
of "Alice in Wonderland") invented
a formulation or logical version of
the paradox of Achilles and the tortoise that,
I bet you anything, most of
you won't know.  In his article "
What the Tortoise Said to Achilles" (published
in 1895 in the philosophical journal Mind),
Carroll depicts a fictional dialogue between
Achilles and the tortoise once the race,
contrary to Zeno's hypothesis, has ended with
the former winning.  The tortoise tries to
get revenge against Achilles by getting
him into a logical problem based on the following
argument by Euclid: (A) Two things that are
equal to a third are equal to each other;
(B) Two sides of this triangle are
equal to the third.  From which it follows,
or so most people claim,
(Z) The two sides of this triangle
are equal to each other.  But in reality,
says the turtle, in this reasoning there
is an implicit premise hidden which,
if we do not accept, the truth of the conclusion does not follow
: the conditional proposition "If A
and B are true, then Z is true."
Let's call this new premise "C" and add it
to the reasoning.  Can we now get
to the truth of Z?  No, says the tortoise,
unless we accept another conditional proposition
D: "If A, B, and C are true, then Z is
true."  But in that case, we will still have to
add E: "If A, B, C and D are true,
then Z is true."  And you see where
this is going, right?  We will have to keep adding
and adding and adding propositions to
infinity and we can never reach the conclusion.
Although most people think that this
is a reasoning that can be solved and
followed in two or three steps, in reality it involves
taking an infinite number of steps and, therefore,
since infinity cannot be followed, we can
never reach the conclusion.  It's the race between
E: Yeah, yeah, sure... The Sorites paradox.
This is actually a family of
paradoxes that play with the vagueness
of concepts in language or
common sense.  Imagine, for example,
a pile of sand.  "Sorites" in
Greek means just that:
a pile.  If we remove a grain
of sand, is it still a pile?  It
would seem so, right?  What if I
take another one away?  Well, that's it too,
isn't it?  Now, if I remove grains
of sand one by one successively,
at some point I will stop having a pile
of sand.  But the question is exactly
when that happens.  It cannot be at
any specific time, because one grain of
sand plus one grain of sand less never makes
a relevant difference.  So
how do we fix this?
L: Imagine the following case as well
.  An evil and despicable being
without scruples kidnaps Jorge Guillermo
Federico Hegel and pulls out his
hair one by one.  At what
point did Hegel go bald?
And it's not worth answering that in none because he's
the f**king boss, okay? This is a serious issue.
E: And notice that, if we invert the paradox, we
still get the same result.  A grain
of sand is obviously not a heap of sand, and if we
add another grain of sand we don't have a heap either.  Now,
if we keep adding
grains of sand one by one, at what
point do I have a pile there if
one more grain of sand never
makes a relevant difference to what came before?
(6) The paradox of Dion and Theon.
This paradox is a bit gory.
"I feel a little bit of...
pressure here in my chest."  It
is attributed to the Stoic philosopher Chrysippus and
says the following.  Let's imagine a
person called "Dion" and let's call
"Theon" that part of him that consists of
all of Dion except the left foot.  One day,
Dion's left foot is amputated.  But now
we have two numerically distinct objects,
Dion and Theon, which not only occupy the same
space, but are both composed of the
same matter.  And that seems kind of absurd, it doesn't make
much sense to say that this person is Dion
AND Theon at the same time, because there is something that is
true of Dion that is not true of Theon, namely:
that Dion's left foot has been amputated.
Theon, on the other hand, has not lost any limbs, he
remains the same.  So one of the two
must have ceased to exist, but the
question is… which one?  Whatever we say, the
answer will be very counterintuitive.  If we say
that Theon has ceased to exist, it will seem
absurd, because he has not undergone any change, he
remains the same.  But it would also be absurd to
say that it is Dion who has ceased to exist,
because he has only lost one foot!  Would we really
want to say that it is enough for a person to
lose a limb for him to disappear
completely?  At the very least it seems a little extreme.
So where's the problem?  What are
the assumptions that are generating the problem?
In a small town far from the hand of God there
is a barber who has a very simple rule:
he shaves all those people who do not
shave themselves.  The question then
is… does the barber shave himself?  Yes or no?
L: Well, if he shaved himself, he
wouldn't have to shave,
but if he doesn't shave himself,
then... screw you!  E: Put this way, it is
a popularization of
Russell's famous paradox, which destabilized
the entire edifice of mathematics by calling into question
the consistency of set theory.
The set of all sets that do not
contain themselves… does it contain
itself or not?  If it doesn't contain itself,
then by definition it has to contain
itself, but if it does contain itself,
then also by definition it doesn't
contain itself and, well... you get the picture.
Where are you going?
L: Let's see
Evangelion!  It's much easier to understand.
(8) The liar's paradox.
If the barber's paradox
has left you with a
headache, you would have been one of the first to beat up
poor Epimenides when he was in the 16th century.  VI a.
C. came up with something as funny
as "All Cretans are liars."
Being Cretan, was he telling the truth or
was he lying?  Epimenides kicks
off the family of liar paradoxes,
which throughout history have been many and
varied.  For example, "This sentence is false"…
is it true or false?  If we have a piece of paper that
says "What is written on the
other side is true" and we turn it over and
read "What is written on the other side is
false"... what are we supposed to understand?
And we end, now yes, with two paradoxes
that I think most of you will not
know because, as I said before, I have
not seen them explained on YouTube.
(9) Moore's paradox.
Listen carefully to the following proposition:
"It is raining but I think it is not raining."
[I've never heard this phrase before and I find it
fascinating.] If someone were to say this seriously, it
would seem absurd, right?
No one can seriously say that it is raining, that
is, acknowledge that it is raining, but at the
same time say that he believes it is not raining.
But here there seems to be a problem, because this
proposition is perfectly consistent, it does not
contain any contradiction.  It is perfectly
possible that it is indeed raining and at the
same time I believe that it is not raining.  Another
way to look at the paradox is as follows.  It
is not absurd to say, in the past tense, "It was raining and
I thought it wasn't raining."  It's also not absurd to
say it in the second person or the third person,
like, "It's raining and you think it's not
raining" or "It's raining and he thinks it's not
raining."  But, on the other hand, it is absurd to
say, in the present tense and in the first person, that it is
raining and I think it is not raining.
Why is it absurd to affirm this proposition,
but not to affirm the rest?
Therein lies Moore's paradox.  (10) The
Langford-Moore paradox or the analysis paradox.
Finally, a paradox about conceptual analysis.
In philosophy, "conceptual analysis" is understood as
something like the definition of a concept in
terms of other concepts.  And it is assumed that
if we were to do a
correct and complete conceptual analysis of a concept,
the result should have exactly the same
meaning as the original concept.  That is to say,
for it to be correct, the analysis or definition
must be able to replace the original concept in
any context without the meaning changing one iota
in each of these sentences.
Now, for this type of analysis to be
useful, it has to be informative, that is, it
has to tell us something that we don't
already know beforehand.  And the paradox is that,
with these definitions, it seems that
absolutely no analysis can be
both correct and informative.  Let us consider
the following example of conceptual analysis:
"For all x, x is a husband if
and only if x is a male spouse."
Based on what we have seen before, we could
say that the analysis is correct because
"husband" represents the same concept
as "male spouse."  And at first glance,
at least, it would seem that it is also informative,
because both expressions are not absolutely
identical.  Now, if this proposition 1
is, indeed, a correct analysis,
then "husband" and "male spouse" would have to
be absolutely interchangeable in any
context.  Which would give us (2) For all x, x is
a husband if and only if x is a husband.  What is the
problem?  That 2 is clearly not an
informative proposition, because it is a tautology.  Therefore,
either 1 is not really an
informative proposition, or the two expressions are not
interchangeable, because they would transform an
informative proposition into a non-informative one,
so that 1 could not be a correct analysis.
Therefore, it appears that no conceptual analysis
can be both correct and informative,
which raises serious doubts either about
the usefulness of conceptual analysis or
about its effectiveness.  And these have been
10 classic paradoxes from the History of
Philosophy that you absolutely have to know.  Tell me in the
comments which one you find most complex and feel free
to try to solve them.  If you liked
the video, click here and subscribe and
activate the bell, because that way YouTube will
notify you every time I upload new content,
and here I leave you another video so that
you can run right now to watch it,
because that way you will continue eating your
brains with more and more philosophy.
And nothing else, goodbye, friends!  Knock, knock.
SUBSCRIBE 🙏